<?xml version="1.0"?>
<content>
 <area description= "The Gate House">
	<bullet text = "Built in 1888 during the rule of Queen Victoria without any military or historical use, but simply in an attempt to make the castle more picturesque.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The retractable draw bridge provided for the Gatehouse was the last drawbridge to be built in Scotland.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Bronze Statues of Robert the Bruce and William Wallace were added to either sides of the entrance in 1929 to mark the 600th anniversary of Bruce's death."  />
		
</area>
 			
 <area description = "The Portcullis Gate">
	<bullet text = "Built from 1571-3, it became the principle gateway into the castle.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;It was built over the ruins of the medieval Constable's Tower, and has two doors, and iron portcullis and another door at the rear.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Renaissance decorations adorn the gate and include the arms of the Earl of Morton, who was Regent of Scotland at the time it was built.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The upper section of the gate is the Argyle Tower, and was added in 1887." />
 </area>
 

  <area description = "Cart Shed / Red Coat Cafe">
	<bullet text = "Built after the Battle of Culloden that ended the 1745-6 Jacobite Rising.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Originally open-fronted, it held 50 carts that brought supplies to the large garrison form suppliers in the town.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;It has served as a barracks, an ammunition store and now a cafe." />
</area>
  
 
   <area description = "Governor's House">
	<bullet text = "Built in 1742 for the castle Governor.  The low wings on either side were to house the Master Gunner and Store-keeper.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;After the post of governor was abolished in 1860, the nursing sisters of the castle hospital used the building.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Today it serves as officers' mess with part reserved for the governor, a Crown appointment restored for purely ceremonial purposes in 1935." />

  </area>
 
    <area description = "New Barracks">
	<bullet text = "Built from 1796-1799 to meet the need of the British army.   The army was expanding quickly at that time, because of the threat that Napoleon posed to Britain.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;At the time they were build, the barracks could hold an entire infantry battalion (600 officers and men)  It still serves a variety of military purposes." /> 
</area>
  
 
     <area description = "Foog's Gate">
	<bullet text = "Built in the 17th c, it is the main entry into the Upper ward.  Before it was built, the only access to the Upper Ward was the Lang Stairs.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The gates original name was 'Foggy Gate' which may have referred to the thick sea-mist that surrounded the castle rock from time to time.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The wall on either side of Foog's Gate was build by Charles II.  It has holes for the cannons and slits for muskets." /> 
</area>
  
   
 
      <area description = "St. Margaret's Chapel">
	<bullet text = "Built by David I around 1124 to honour his saintly mother the former queen Margaret. The chapel is the oldest remaining structure in the castle.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;For many years, it was not a free standing building, but was linked up with other building and used for many other purposes.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;In the 16th c it was converted into a gunpowder store, and the stone vaulted ceiling dated from that time.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;In 1845 the chapel's original purpose was discovered and it was restored to the condition that we today.&lt;/li&gt;" />
</area>
  
 

<area description = "Half Moon Battery">
	<bullet text = "Wrapped around the ruins of David's Tower which was destroyed in the siege of 1573, the Half Moon Battery was built to serve as the castle's high-level defense on its most vulnerable eastern front.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The Half Moon Battery was badly damaged in a siege on the Castle in 1689.   Major rebuilding took place soon after, to rebuild the Battery into what we see today." /> 
</area>
  

 
 
       <area description = "National War Memorial">
	<bullet text = "One of the most modern building in the Castle, the War Memorial in it's present condition dates from the 1920's.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;On this site was the mediaeval church of St. Mary, which was converted into a munition house in the 16th century.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The shell of the existing building, thought very hard to distinguish, was erected in 1755 as a barracks.  The decision to convert it into a War Memorial was made after the Great War of 1914-18." /> 

</area>
  
 
        <area description = "Royal Apartments">
	<bullet text = "Royalty has been using the south-east corner of the castle for their private accomodation since at least the 14th century.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;It began as an extension to David's tower, but was later enlarged to become the royal residence itself.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;In 1566, it was modified for Queen Mary, who stayed in the Royal Apartments during the birth of her son James VI.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The last sovereign to sleep here was Charles I in 1633, the night before his Scottish coronation." /> 
</area>
 
 
   <area description = "Great Hall">
	<bullet text = "Built in 1511 by James IV, the Great Hall was constructed to be the chief place of ceremony within the castle.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;In 1650, the Hall was converted into a barracks by Cromwell, and the barracks entrance, now the blocked-up arched doorway in the center of the building, is still visible today.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;After Cromwell, the Hall was turned into a hospital around the beginning of the 18th c, and a floor was inserted into the structure making it a 2 story building.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Finally, between 1887-1891, the Hall was restored.  The only remaining section of the original Great Hall is the intricate hammerbeam roof.  It is one of the most important medieval roofs in Britain today.&lt;/li&gt;" />

 </area> 
 
 <area description = "Queen Anne Building">
	<bullet text = "In medieval times, this was the site of the Royal Gunhouse.  Mons Meg would have been stored here when she arrived at the castle.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;By 1700 the Gunhouse was gone and in 1708, after the Jacobite rising, the current building was constructed.  The building originally provided accommodation for military officers as well as barracks for the castle gunners.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Today the building is home to the castle's education unit, a cafˆ© and also the entrance to the Prisons of War exhibition in the Castle Vaults.&lt;/li&gt;" /> 

 </area>
 
</content> 